Guide to the Irwin Silver Photographs 1975-2002 PR 209
New-York Historical Society
Irwin Silver photographs
1975-2002
New-York Historical Society
Silver, Irwin, 1945-
PR 209
4.84 Linear feet in 4 boxes
The collection includes four series of photographs taken by Irwin Silver from 1975-2002. These include memorials related to firefighters and other victims of the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center towers; New York City at night; Central Park in all four seasons; and a portfolio of images taken on Sundays.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the photographer, Irwin Silver, 1994, 2003, 2017, and 2018.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes four series of photographs taken by Irwin Silver from 1975-2002, with a few other of his photographs. One series concerns memorials related to firefighters and other victims of the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center towers. Another series includes images of New York City at night. The third series includes various subjects unified under the subject of images taken on Sundays. Most of the photographs were taken in Manhattan, with some in Brooklyn, Bronx, Queens, and Hoboken. The fourth series is of Central Park, with photographs of its natural elements and built environment taken in all four seasons.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series:
Series I. New York City September 11 Memorials, 2001-2002
Series II. General Photographs, 1977-2002
Series III. Portfolio I: Sundays, 1975-1979
Series IV. Nightwalks, 1979-1990
Series V. Central Park, 1991-1994
Central Park (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; World Trade Center Site (New York, N.Y.); Fire fighters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Memorials -- New York (State) -- New York.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Photographs.; New York (N.Y.). Fire Department. Vulcan Society
- Series I: New York City September 11 Memorials, 2001-2002
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains the thirty-six images comprising the photographer's series Memorial Wall. The photographs are all black and white, silver gelatin 11x14" prints, and show memorials for people who died during the World Trade Center collapse on September 11, 2001. Many show public and private memorials to firefighters. Others show more public memorials, such as a fence where memorial tiles were hung. All the photographs were taken in 2001-2002.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The 18 photographs in folders 1-3 were donated by Irwin Silver in 2003; the 18 photographs in folders 4-6 were donated in 2017.
  Related Materials
  Other photographs of the World Trade Center and the aftermath of its destruction can be found in PR 169, the World Trade Center Photograph Collection.
  - Memorial sheet, St. Paul's Chapel Gate, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nereida De Jesus, memorial wall, St. Paul's Church, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Snowman and memorial wall, St. Paul's Chapel Gate, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorial wall, St. Paul's Chapel Gate, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family on Church and Park Place on "viewing platform" line, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rescue 1, NYFD, Memorial, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transit Police District Four, NYPD, Memorial, Union Square Subway Station, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Children's art, Victim's Assistance Center, 51 Chambers Street, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Firefighter Reuben David Correa, Engine 74, W. 83rd Street, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Engine Company 3, Ladder Company 12, 7th Battalion, NYFD, Memorial, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Aid memorial with portrait of Captain Patrick J. Brown, Union Square Subway Station, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Aid memorial with portrait of James Francis Quinn, Union Square Subway Station, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Court Officers Memorial, New York State Supreme Court, 111 Centre Street (copy 1), 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tiles on fence, Greenwich House Project, 7th Avenue and Greenwich Avenue, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tiles on fence (long shot), Greenwich House Project, 7th Avenue and Greenwich Avenue, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interior, Rescue 2, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fire Engine Door (salvaged from World Trade Center) memorial, Rescue 2, NYFD, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - African-American Firefighters Memorial, Vulcan Hall, Eastern Parkway and Kingston Avenue, Brooklyn, 2002 September (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wreath with woman's portrait on fence at Broadway and Cedar, 2001 December (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wreath with Charlie Heeran's portrait on fence at Broadway and Cedar, 2001 December (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Facade with flag salvaged from World Trade Center, Engine 6, FDNY, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial wall (with portrait of Firefighter Raymond York) St. Paul's Chapel gate, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial wall in snow, St. Paul's Chapel gate, 2002 January (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Children's art, Union Square subway station, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial, Engine 8 and Ladder 2 Firehouse, FDNY, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Art Aid memorial wall with angel and Jeffrey Coale's name, Union Square subway station, 2002 March (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Shamrock in sidewalk for Jimmy Riches, Firefighter, Engine 18, Fifth Avenue, Brooklyn, 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mural, Red Hook, Brooklyn, 2002 April (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorial, Ladder Company 131, Engine Company 279, FDNY, 2002 April (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Art Aid memorial with portrait of Firefighter William Wren, Union Square subway station, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Court Officers Memorial, New York State Supreme Court, 111 Centre Street (copy 2), 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Children's art, Court Officers Memorial Wall, New York State Supreme Court, 111 Centre Street, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interior Memorial, Sixth Precinct House, NYPD, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tile angels on fence, Greenwich House Project, 7th and Greenwich Avenues, 2002, May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Firefighter John Bergin, Engine Company 9, Ladder Company 6, Chinatown, FDNY, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interior Memorial, Engine Company 9, Ladder Company 6, Chinatown, FDNY, 2002 May (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: General Photographs, 1977-2002
  Series II contains three photographs of New York City, which date from 1977 to 2002. Two black and white images from 1977 and 1990 show New York street scenes from the Lower East Side. A color chromogenic type C print, taken in 2002, shows a replica of the Statue of Liberty being transported from the roof of the Liberty Storage Warehouse on West 64th Street to the Brooklyn Museum of Art.
  The Hanover Street and Orchard Street photographs were gifts of the photographer in 1994. The Statue of Liberty was a gift of the photographer in 2003.
  - Replica of Statue of Liberty, 2002 February (Offsite-box 1, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hanover Street, NYC, Autumn 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Orchard Street New York City, June 5, 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III. Portfolio I: Sundays, 1975-1979; 1.5 Linear feet in one portfolio box
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds a portfolio, in its original case, of 10 gelatin silver prints, all numbered as 12/20 and signed by the photographer, Irwin Silver. Includes opening text with titles and dates of the works, with a statement of the project's background and purpose. The photographs were taken from 1975-1978, and the text written and portfolio produced in 1979. The container list includes the titles as documented in the portfolio.
  Arrangement
  The photographs are in the sequence as numbered by the photographer.
  Gift of the photographer, Irwin Silver, April 2018.
  - Rusted iron, West Side Highway, New York, New York, Spring 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 1)
  - Sandstone, Hoboken, New Jersey, Spring 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 2)
  - Sandstone, Hoboken, New Jersey, Summer 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 3)
  - Jetty rocks, Coney Island, Brooklyn, New York, Fall 1975 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 4)
  - Trees and foliage, Brooklyn, New York, Summer 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 5)
  - Flour warehouse, Hoboken, New Jersey, Spring 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 6)
  - Hanover Street, New York, New York, Fall 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 7)
  - Plymouth Street, Brooklyn, New York, Winter 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 8)
  - Sunset, Hudson, New York, Fall 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 9)
  - Skyline, New York Harbor and environs, Summer 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Box 3, Item 10)
- Series IV. Nightwalks, 1979-1990
  The series includes 57 gelatin silver photographs from Irwin Silver's project Nightwalks. These black and white photographs from 1979 to 1990 are of subway entrances, storefronts, entrances to corporate buildings, street scenes, and other images of New York City (mostly Manhattan, but some Brooklyn, Bronx, and Queens) as they appeared to the photographer in the late night and early morning hours. The container list identifies all the photographs in the series with the photographer's description. The series also includes a document written by Irwin Silver in which he reflects on the project generally and on the context of some of the specific photographs.
  The container list below lists the descriptions of the photographs as given by Irwin Silver, in chronological order. The photographs themselves are arranged roughly by size in two folders: Folder 7 holds photographs that are approximately 7 x 9 inches, or smaller. Folder 8 holds photographs that are approximately 11 x 14 inches, or somewhat smaller. Irwin's reflections on the project and his list of the photographs are in a third folder.
  Gift of Irwin Silver, June 2018.
  Credit line to be used for the photographs in this series: "Gift of the photographer in memory of Barbara Millstein."
  - Moonset at Dawn, Brooklyn, New York, February 14, 1979, 6:40 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subway Entrance, AT&T Building, NYC, October 7, 1979, 4:45 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subway Entrance, Grand Central, NYC, April 13, 1980, 8 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subway Kiosk, Bowling Green, NYC, June 20, 1980, 7:30 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - El Station at Dusk, Woodside, New York, September 28, 1980, 6:45 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Eagle Restaurant, NYC, September 19, 1981,1:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Municipal Building, Brooklyn, New York, September 26, 1981, 9 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company, NYC, October 2, 1981, 11:45 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Doyers Street, NYC, January 15, 1982, 4:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Square Diner, NYC, February 21, 1982, 4 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Municipal Building, NYC, April 4, 1982, 5 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chrysler Building, NYC, April 4, 1982, 5:45 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Delmonico's, NYC, February 5, 1983, 8 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - El Station, Bronx, New York, May 28, 1983, 1:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Federal Hall National Monument, NYC, July 23, 1983, 11 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Macy's Herald Square, NYC, August 6, 1983, 1:45 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fulton Fish Market, South Street, NYC, August 24, 1983, 11:50 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Street Clock, Fifth Avenue & 44th Street, NYC, October 13, 1983, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Plaza Street, Brooklyn, New York, October 13, 1983, 3 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Crosby & Prince Streets, NYC, May 26, 1985, 12:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M. Citarella Fish Market, NYC, June 2, 1985, 1:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Radio City Music Hall, NYC, June 10, 1985, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Royal Machinery Exchange, NYC, July 2, 1985, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Harry Chong Laundry, NYC, August 22, 1985, 3:45 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jimmy's Fruit Store, NYC, August 28, 1985, 2:45 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gallery, Spring & Mercer Streets, NYC, April 13, 1986, 3:15 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fretta Bros. Sausage Shop, NYC, June 1, 1986, 5 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mott Street, NYC, June 1, 1986, 5 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsstand, Brooklyn, New York, October 24, 1986, 7 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Broadway Barber Shop, NYC, April 5, 1987, 2:15 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Entrance, A. Lewis Thread Company Building, NYC, May 10, 1987, 3 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Revolving Door, Rockefeller Center, NYC, May 16, 1987, 1:40 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clock, Rockefeller Center, NYC, May 23, 1987, 12:20 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Associated Press Building with Isamu Noguchi Sculpture "News," Rockefeller Center, NYC, May 24, 1987, 12:15 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Windsor Florist, NYC, June 14, 1987, 1:50 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Seagram Building, NYC, June 28, 1987, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Entrance, International Telephone Building, NYC, July 18, 1987, 2 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vesuvio Bakery, NYC, July 24, 1987, 11;40 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Parking Lot, West 31st Street, NYC, August 1, 1987, 12:40 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Approach, Queensboro Bridge, NYC, August 8, 1987, 3 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Entrance, the French Building, NYC, August 16, 1987, 12:55 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Entrance, Directors Guild of America Building, NYC, August 30, 1987, 12:50 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - East 41st Street & Third Avenue, NYC, September 6, 1987, 3:05 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - West 21st Street between 10th & 11th Avenues, NYC, November 1, 1987, 9 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subway Entrance, Bowery Savings Bank Building, NYC, May 7, 1988, 11:30 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Storefronts, Madison Avenue and 67th Street, NYC, May 7, 1988, 2:50 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hybrid Flowers, NYC, May 9, 1988, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Soldiers, Sailors & Airmen's Club, NYC, May 28, 1988, 2 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Garfield Place, Brooklyn, New York, August 2, 1988, 12:20 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gramercy Park South & Irving Place, NYC, September 5, 1988, 4:30 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - La Marionetta, NYC, October 10, 1988, 3 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Church of the Transfiguration, NYC, July 1, 1989, 10 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Entrance, MONY Building, NYC, July 3, 1989, 2:25 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Entrance, 3 West 57th Street, NYC, July 3, 1989, 3:40 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - West Side Highway, Pier 99, NYC, July 9, 1989, 4 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hanover Street, NYC, July 19, 1989, 1 AM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Park Avenue Viaduct at 33rd Street, NYC, May 28, 1990, 8 PM (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Background Text for Nightwalks, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series V. Central Park, 1991-1994
  101 color 8x10 inch photographs of Central Park scenes. The photos are undated, but in his transmittal the donor/photographer noted that they dated from 1991-1994, with most taken in 1991-92. The photographs are of both the park's natural elements (foliage, rock formations (including detailed close-ups of rock textures and colors), lawns, waterfalls, lakes/ponds) and built environment (statuary (including Alice in Wonderland), bridges (including Bow Bridge), fountains (including Bethesda), lampposts, walkways, benches, roads, gazebos). Familiar sites (Bethesda, Alice in Wonderland, Bow Bride) are represented, but most of the views are of the more typical general views of park features. Certainly not typical of the park is that the photographs are notably devoid of people and animals, even at popular spots such as the Mall and Belvedere Castle), thereby focusing on the park itself. The photos also include several that include the buildings just outside the park, with the park's features as foreground. All four seasons of the year are represented so many photos capture the park in the white of snow and in autumn colors, as well as the lush green of summer and the color of spring blooms.
  Gift of Irwin Silver, October 2018.
  - Central Park Photographs (Color prints), 1991-1994 (Offsite-box 1, Box 4)
  - Central Park Photographs (Digital files on CD). RESTRICTED, 1991-1994 (Offsite-box 1, Box 4)